<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<codeBook xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5"  version="2.5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <docDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Metadata record for Randomized Controlled Trial of Breakfast Recommendations on Weight: A Multi-Site Effectiveness Trial</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">36174</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <producer abbr="ICPSR">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</producer>
                <copyright>ICPSR metadata records are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 United States License <ExtLink URI="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/"/>..</copyright>
            </prodStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2015-08-07">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
        </citation>
    </docDscr>
    <stdyDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Randomized Controlled Trial of Breakfast Recommendations on Weight: A Multi-Site Effectiveness Trial</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">36174</IDNo>
                <IDNo agency="datacite">http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR36174.v1</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <rspStmt>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Alabama-Birmingham">Allison, David B.</AuthEnty>
            </rspStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <copyright> <ExtLink URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/36174/terms">ICPSR Terms of Use</ExtLink></copyright>
            </prodStmt>
            <distStmt>
                <distrbtr abbr="ICPSR" affiliation="Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan">Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</distrbtr>
                <distDate date="2024-11-05"/>
            </distStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2015-08-07">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2018-02-15">2018-02-15</version>
                <notes>2018-02-15 The citation of this study may have changed due to the new version control system that has been implemented. The previous citation was: Allison, David B. Randomized Controlled Trial of Breakfast Recommendations on Weight: A Multi-Site Effectiveness Trial. ICPSR36174-v1. Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2015-08-07. http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR36174.v1</notes>
            </verStmt>
            <biblCit>
  Allison, David B. Randomized Controlled Trial of Breakfast Recommendations on Weight: A Multi-Site Effectiveness Trial. Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2015-08-07. https://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR36174.v1
</biblCit>
            <holdings URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/36174"></holdings>
        </citation>
        <stdyInfo>
            <subject>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">diet</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">eating habits</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health behavior</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">nutrition</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">obesity</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">public health</keyword>
            </subject>
            <abstract contentType="abstract">This study is a multi-site, 3 parallel arm, randomized, controlled trial. The study was conducted over sixteen weeks. Body weight and height were measured at the beginning of the trial, and body weight again at the end of the trial period. Three hundred and twenty four participants were enrolled, with each of six sites randomizing fifty four participants, with equal allocation of participants randomized to the breakfast, no breakfast, and control groups. The first subject contact included the initial telephone screening, in which participants who passed the level of screening and were interested in proceeding were invited and scheduled for a clinical screening visit. Participants who were passed into the clinical screening were consented and then height, weight, and BMI were measured. Participants were also randomized into the control, breakfast, and no breakfast groups during this time. The study then had 3 telephone calls, all 3 weeks apart (4-week telephone call, 8-week telephone call, 12-week telephone call), in which they were asked about their weight loss from time of last contact, if they had any problems/adverse reactions, or any questions. During the 16th week (final visit), weight was measured, their diaries collected, and participants were compensated for their time. Demographic information collected includes age, sex,  and ethnicity.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="purpose">PURPOSE OF THE STUDY: The purpose of the study was to determine if breakfast consumption recommendations can produce weight loss, and if that weight loss was dependent on typical breakfast consumption patterns.</abstract>
            <sumDscr>
                <timePrd event="single" date="2013"/>
                <collDate event="start" cycle="C1" date="2013-01-07"/>
                <collDate event="end" cycle="C1" date="2013-12-11"/>
                <geogCover>New York City</geogCover>
                <geogCover>United States</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Massachusetts</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Colorado</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Denver</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Alabama</geogCover>
                <geogCover>New York (state)</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Birmingham</geogCover>
                <geogCover>Boston</geogCover>
                <geogUnit>site (university)</geogUnit>
                <anlyUnit>Individual</anlyUnit>
                <universe>Healthy overweight adults with a Body Mass Index (BMI) greater than 35. </universe>
                <dataKind>experimental data</dataKind>
            </sumDscr>
        </stdyInfo>
        <method>
            <dataColl>
                <sampProc>Participants were recruited by convenience sampling: flyers, posters, advertisements in local area newspapers, mailings, existing databases of person who have expressed interest in weight-loss interventions, and word of mouth.</sampProc>
                <collMode>face-to-face interview</collMode>
                <collMode> on-site questionnaire</collMode>
                <collMode> telephone interview</collMode>
                <weight>None</weight>
            </dataColl>
            <anlyInfo>
                <respRate>43 percent of screened individuals participated.</respRate>
            </anlyInfo>
        </method>
        <dataAccs>
            <setAvail media="online">
                <accsPlac URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/36174">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</accsPlac>
            </setAvail>
            <useStmt>
                <specPerm>Additional special permissions, where applicable, are described in the restrictions field </specPerm>
                <restrctn>Access to these data is restricted. Users interested in obtaining these data must complete a Restricted Data Use Agreement,specify the reason for the request, and obtain IRB approval or notice of exemption for their research.</restrctn>
            </useStmt>
        </dataAccs>
        <notes>These  data are freely available to data users at ICPSR member institutions. The curation  and dissemination of this study are provided by the institutional members of ICPSR. How do I access ICPSR data if I am not at a member institution?</notes>
    </stdyDscr>
</codeBook>