<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<codeBook xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5"  version="2.5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <docDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Metadata record for Post Coital DNA Recovery in Minority Proxy Couples, United States, 2014-2018</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">37250</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <producer abbr="ICPSR">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</producer>
                <copyright>ICPSR metadata records are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 United States License <ExtLink URI="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/"/>..</copyright>
            </prodStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2019-12-17">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
        </citation>
    </docDscr>
    <stdyDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Post Coital DNA Recovery in Minority Proxy Couples, United States, 2014-2018</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">37250</IDNo>
                <IDNo agency="datacite">http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR37250.v1</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <rspStmt>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Alabama in Birmingham">Speck, Patricia M.</AuthEnty>
            </rspStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <copyright> <ExtLink URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/37250/terms">ICPSR Terms of Use</ExtLink></copyright>
                <fundAg>United States Department of Justice. Office of Justice Programs. National Institute of Justice</fundAg>
                <grantNo agency="United States Department of Justice. Office of Justice Programs. National Institute of Justice">2014-NE-BX-0009</grantNo>
            </prodStmt>
            <distStmt>
                <distrbtr abbr="ICPSR" affiliation="Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan">Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</distrbtr>
                <distDate date="2024-11-05"/>
            </distStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2019-12-17">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
            <biblCit>
  Speck, Patricia M. Post Coital DNA Recovery in Minority Proxy Couples, United States, 2014-2018.  [distributor], 2019-12-17. https://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR37250.v1
</biblCit>
            <holdings URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/37250"></holdings>
        </citation>
        <stdyInfo>
            <subject>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">genetics data</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">reproductive history</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">sexually transmitted disease</keyword>
            </subject>
            <abstract contentType="abstract">Introduction and Background. Minorities are less likely to report
rapes. The Post Coital DNA Recovery (PCDR) study (2009-14) subjects were white
(93%) where expanded collection times were not generalizable to minority
populations. Evidence reports health and medical differences between races
necessitating duplication of previous research in minority populations.
Aims.
(1) What is the time period in which it is
possible to collect post-coital DNA in minority women using Y-STR laboratory
methods? and (2) when compared to the former study sample of minority and
non-minority, what are the physiological conditions, factors, or activities in
minority couples that influence post-coital DNA recovery?
Design. The design includes mixed methods duplication
perfected in the first study, embracing descriptive and inferential techniques.
Qualitative research used semi-structured interviews. Aim 1 analysis used PCDR-M
data only. Aim 2 combined data from both PCDR and PCDR-M studies. Combined, DNA
recovery, a binary outcome accounting for repeated methods in population
regression analysis, used Generalized Estimating Equation (GEE) methods.
Fidelity.
The strict criteria for adherence included considerable outreach and
support of study personnel. PCDR and PCDR-M data combined and compared the two
samples, which had specific homogeneity, including same inclusion and
elimination criteria in both studies; fidelity to the validated protocol;
laboratory method and interpretation for inclusion; duplicate statistical
analysis; and interpretation of data. Any variation in key variables met
elimination criteria.
Assumptions and Limitations. Assumptions included (1) motivation is altruistic; (2)
motivation is incentives and coercion for some; (3) negotiating coitus is
difficult and stressful; and (4) similar fidelity and dropout rates. The
limitations included (1) a lack of representation for the diverse experiences
of rape victims; (2) sample size; (3) self-selection bias; (4) protocol adherence;
and (4) advances in laboratory science and DNA kits.
Demographics. Demographic variables included gender, race, and age. Major categories in the dataset included participants' reproductive history, data on female participants' reproductive organs, and childhood abuse.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="purpose">PURPOSE OF THE STUDY: Aims.
(1) What is the time period in which it is
possible to collect post-coital DNA in minority women using Y-STR laboratory
methods? and (2) when compared to the former study sample of minority and
non-minority, what are the physiological conditions, factors, or activities in
minority couples that influence post-coital DNA recovery.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="mixed">STUDY DESIGN: The design includes mixed methods duplication
perfected in the first study, embracing descriptive and inferential techniques.
Qualitative research used semi-structured interviews. Aim 1 analysis used PCDR-M
data only. Aim 2 combined data from both PCDR and PCDR-M studies. Combined, DNA
recovery, a binary outcome accounting for repeated methods in population
regression analysis, used Generalized Estimating Equation (GEE) methods.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="mixed">DESCRIPTION OF VARIABLES: The dataset ACE contains variables related to childhood abuse.
The datasets Allele2018 and DNA_C contain variables related to cervix and fornix analysis.
The datasets Demo_combined and Phi contain demographic variables.
The datasets F_Reproductive_History and M_Reproductive_History contain variables related to the sexual health history and reproductive history of participants.
The dataset HERS contains variables related to the Hymen Estrogen Response Scale (HERS).</abstract>
            <sumDscr>
                <timePrd event="start" cycle="C1" date="2014"/>
                <timePrd event="end" cycle="C1" date="2018"/>
                <collDate event="start" cycle="C1" date="2014"/>
                <collDate event="end" cycle="C1" date="2018"/>
                <geogCover>United States</geogCover>
                <geogUnit>Zip Code</geogUnit>
                <anlyUnit>Individual</anlyUnit>
                <universe>Monogamous couples in the United States. </universe>
                <dataKind>clinical data</dataKind>
                <dataKind>observational data</dataKind>
            </sumDscr>
        </stdyInfo>
        <method>
            <dataColl>
                <timeMeth>Cross-sectional</timeMeth>
                <sampProc>A local recruitment of minority proxy couples occurred through organizational networks and media.  Volunteer proxy couples called the study phone to express interest, and the caller was screened for eligibility. Recruitment and screening questions eliminated those with full hysterectomy (must have a cervix), male vasectomy or infertility (must have sperm DNA) and obesity (which lowers sperm count). If not self-eliminated, interested couples and collectors contacted the Principle Investigator (PI) or co-investigator where a telephone discussion about the study and protocol for IRB approved informed consent occurred. Participants received consent paperwork through the U S Post Office or email following the screening, determination of eligibility, and telephone-consent to receive the materials according to their preference, which included IRB-approved consent forms with tagged signature and initials locations for individual male and female participants.   Once the PI received the signed consents from both couple-members, each participant completed the questionnaire and demographic survey. The PI determined eligibility and if eligible, provided study paperwork and supplies, which included the protocol, a diary card, pH strips, cotton-tipped applicators, and collector forms, and study directions to the female participant in the couple.</sampProc>
                <collMode>coded on-site observation</collMode>
                <collMode> face-to-face interview</collMode>
                <collMode> mail questionnaire</collMode>
                <collMode> self-enumerated questionnaire</collMode>
            </dataColl>
            <notes>This collection is related to the <a
href = " https://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR35254.v1">Longitudinal Post-Coital DNA Recovery 2010-2014 [UNITED STATES], ICPSR 35254.</a> For similar study information and characteristics, please refer
to both studies.</notes>
            <anlyInfo/>
        </method>
        <dataAccs>
            <setAvail media="online">
                <accsPlac URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/37250">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</accsPlac>
            </setAvail>
            <useStmt>
                <specPerm>Additional special permissions, where applicable, are described in the restrictions field </specPerm>
                <restrctn>Access to these data is restricted. Users interested in obtaining these data must complete a Restricted Data Use Agreement,specify the reason for the request, and obtain IRB approval or notice of exemption for their research.</restrctn>
            </useStmt>
        </dataAccs>
        <notes>The public-use data files in this collection are available for access by the general public. Access does not require affiliation with an ICPSR member institution.</notes>
        <notes>One or more files in this data collection have special restrictions. Restricted data files are not available for direct download from the website; click on the Restricted Data button to learn more.</notes>
    </stdyDscr>
</codeBook>