<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<codeBook xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5"  version="2.5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <docDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Metadata record for 2010 United States Census Tract Community Type Classification and Neighborhood Social and Economic Environment Score for 2000 and 2010, from the Diabetes Location, Environmental Attributes, and Disparities (LEAD) Network</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">38645</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <producer abbr="ICPSR">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</producer>
                <copyright>ICPSR metadata records are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 United States License <ExtLink URI="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/"/>..</copyright>
            </prodStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2023-03-07">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
        </citation>
    </docDscr>
    <stdyDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>2010 United States Census Tract Community Type Classification and Neighborhood Social and Economic Environment Score for 2000 and 2010, from the Diabetes Location, Environmental Attributes, and Disparities (LEAD) Network</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">38645</IDNo>
                <IDNo agency="datacite">http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR38645.v1</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <rspStmt>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="Drexel University">McClure, Leslie A.</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="Geisinger Medical Center">Hirsch, Annemarie G.</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="Johns Hopkins University">Schwartz, Brian S.</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="New York University. Grossman School of Medicine">Thorpe, Lorna E.</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="New York University. Grossman School of Medicine">Elbel, Brian</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Alabama at Birmingham">Carson, April</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Alabama at Birmingham">Long, D. Leann</AuthEnty>
            </rspStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <copyright> <ExtLink URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/38645/terms">ICPSR Terms of Use</ExtLink></copyright>
                <fundAg>United States Department of Health and Human Services. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</fundAg>
                <grantNo agency="United States Department of Health and Human Services. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention">Cooperative agreements: U01DP006293 (Drexel University), U01DP006296 (Geisinger-Johns Hopkins University), U01DP006299 (New York University School of Medicine), and U01DP006302 (University of Alabama at Birmingham)</grantNo>
            </prodStmt>
            <distStmt>
                <distrbtr abbr="ICPSR" affiliation="Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan">Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</distrbtr>
                <distDate date="2024-11-05"/>
            </distStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2023-03-07">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
            <biblCit>
  McClure, Leslie A., Hirsch, Annemarie G., Schwartz, Brian S., Thorpe, Lorna E., Elbel, Brian, Carson, April, and Long, D. Leann. 2010 United States Census Tract Community Type Classification and Neighborhood Social and Economic Environment Score for 2000 and 2010, from the Diabetes Location, Environmental Attributes, and Disparities (LEAD) Network. Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2023-03-07. https://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR38645.v1
</biblCit>
            <holdings URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/38645"></holdings>
        </citation>
        <stdyInfo>
            <subject>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">census data</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">census tract level</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">diabetes</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">epidemiology</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">neighborhoods</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">rural areas</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">social environment</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">socioeconomic status</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">urban areas</keyword>
            </subject>
            <abstract contentType="abstract">This dataset contains two measures designed to be used in tandem to characterize United States census tracts, originally developed for use in stratified analyses of the Diabetes Location, Environmental Attributes, and Disparities (LEAD) Network. The first measure is a 2010 tract-level community type categorization based on a modification of Rural-Urban Commuting Area (RUCA) Codes that incorporates census-designated urban areas and tract land area, with five categories: higher density urban, lower density urban, suburban/small town, rural, and undesignated (McAlexander, et al., 2022). The second measure is a neighborhood social and economic environment (NSEE) score, a community-type stratified z-score sum of 6 US census-derived variables, with sums scaled between 0 and 100, computed for the year 2000 and 2010. A tract with a higher NSEE z-score sum indicates more socioeconomic disadvantage compared to a tract with a lower z-score sum. Analysts should not compare NSEE scores across LEAD community types, as values have been computed and scaled within community type.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="purpose">PURPOSE OF THE STUDY: The goal of the LEAD Network was to elucidate the role community-level factors play in observed geographic differences in diabetes incidence and prevalence across the US.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="mixed">STUDY DESIGN: Data used to create the community type measure included Census tract land area from the 2010 Decennial Census (SF1 100% Data, G001 geographic tables), and 2010 Rural-Urban Commuting Area codes from the United States Department of Agriculture (version last updated 7/3/2019).
Data for the 6 Census variables used to compute the Neighborhood Social and Economic Environment Measure were downloaded from the SF3 file of the 2000 Decennial Census and the 2006-2010 American Community Survey (ACS), for the 2000 and 2010 measures respectively. The year 2000 tract data was converted to the 2010 tract boundaries using the interpolation tool from Brown University's Longitudinal Tract Data Base (LTDB), as described in Logan, et al., "Interpolating U.S. Decennial Census Tract Data from as Early as 1970 to 2010: A Longitudinal Tract Database" (2014).
Data for both measures were then mapped to align with the 2016 TIGER Line version of the 2010 tract boundaries from the US Census Bureau's National Sub-State Geography Geodatabase.</abstract>
            <abstract contentType="mixed">DESCRIPTION OF VARIABLES: This dataset contains four main variables: a geographic ID for census tracts, a community type classification, and the two Neighborhood Social and Economic Environment (NSEE) variables. The NSEE measure is a community-type stratified, z-score sum of 6 US Census-derived variables, with sums scaled between 0 and 100.</abstract>
            <sumDscr>
                <timePrd event="start" cycle="C1" date="2000-01-01"/>
                <timePrd event="end" cycle="C1" date="2010-21-31"/>
                <collDate event="start" cycle="C1" date="2019-01-01"/>
                <collDate event="end" cycle="C1" date="2019-21-31"/>
                <geogCover>United States</geogCover>
                <geogUnit>Census Tract</geogUnit>
                <anlyUnit>Geographic Unit</anlyUnit>
                <universe>Census tracts in the contiguous United States. </universe>
                <dataKind>aggregate data</dataKind>
            </sumDscr>
        </stdyInfo>
        <method>
            <dataColl/>
            <anlyInfo/>
        </method>
        <dataAccs>
            <setAvail media="online">
                <accsPlac URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/38645">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</accsPlac>
            </setAvail>
            <useStmt>
                <specPerm>Additional special permissions, where applicable, are described in the restrictions field </specPerm>
                <restrctn>Access to these data is restricted. Users interested in obtaining these data must complete a Restricted Data Use Agreement,specify the reason for the request, and obtain IRB approval or notice of exemption for their research.</restrctn>
            </useStmt>
        </dataAccs>
        <notes>The public-use data files in this collection are available for access by the general public. Access does not require affiliation with an ICPSR member institution.</notes>
    </stdyDscr>
</codeBook>