<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<codeBook xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5"  version="2.5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <docDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Metadata record for Puerto Rican Elder: Health Conditions (PREHCO) Project, 2021-2022</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">39091</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <producer abbr="ICPSR">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</producer>
                <copyright>ICPSR metadata records are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 United States License <ExtLink URI="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/"/>..</copyright>
            </prodStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2024-07-01">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
        </citation>
    </docDscr>
    <stdyDscr>
        <citation>
            <titlStmt>
                <titl>Puerto Rican Elder: Health Conditions (PREHCO) Project, 2021-2022</titl>
                <IDNo agency="ICPSR">39091</IDNo>
                <IDNo agency="datacite">http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR39091.v1</IDNo>
            </titlStmt>
            <rspStmt>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Alabama at Birmingham">Crowe, Michael</AuthEnty>
                <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Puerto Rico">Dávila-Roman, Ana Luisa</AuthEnty>
            </rspStmt>
            <prodStmt>
                <copyright> <ExtLink URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/39091/terms">ICPSR Terms of Use</ExtLink></copyright>
                <fundAg>United States Department of Health and Human Services. National Institutes of Health. National Institute on Aging</fundAg>
                <grantNo agency="United States Department of Health and Human Services. National Institutes of Health. National Institute on Aging">RO1 AG064769</grantNo>
            </prodStmt>
            <distStmt>
                <distrbtr abbr="ICPSR" affiliation="Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan">Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</distrbtr>
                <distDate date="2024-11-05"/>
            </distStmt>
            <verStmt>
                <version date="2024-07-01">V1</version>
            </verStmt>
            <biblCit>
  Crowe, Michael, and Dávila-Roman, Ana Luisa. Puerto Rican Elder: Health Conditions (PREHCO) Project, 2021-2022. Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2024-07-01. https://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR39091.v1
</biblCit>
            <holdings URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/39091"></holdings>
        </citation>
        <stdyInfo>
            <subject>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">cognitive status</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">community health</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">demographic characteristics</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">demographic statistics</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">eldercare</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health attitudes</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health behavior</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health care access</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health problems</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health services utilization</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health status</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">household composition</keyword>
                <keyword vocab="thesaurus">older adults</keyword>
            </subject>
            <abstract contentType="abstract">This is the third wave of the PREHCO project (Puerto Rican Elder Health
Conditions study) and was developed between 2021 and 2022 as a collaboration between the University of Alabama in Birmingham and the University of Puerto Rico. The project began as a cross-sectional study of the non-institutionalized population aged 60 years or older in Puerto Rico. This wave followed the survivors of the 1,299 original participants at the beginning of the fieldwork and aimed to examine the predictors of cognitive decline, disability, and mortality. 
PREHCO was designed as a study comparable to the Multicenter Project on
Health and Well-being of Older Adults in Latin America and the Caribbean (SABE)
developed by the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) in several cities in
Latin America, and with some studies carried out in the United States, mainly
the Health and Retirement Study (HRS). 
For this purpose, a questionnaire was designed that included sections
on health conditions, physical and mental disability, functionality, use of
medicines, health needs and social services, access to and use of health
services, abuse, migration, housing conditions, patterns of help from family,
community and public and government agencies, and others. 
Since its inception, PREHCO has been funded with federal
funds from the National Institute on Aging (NIA). Initially it was a project
between the University of Wisconsin-Madison and the University of Puerto Rico
from 2000-2009. </abstract>
            <abstract contentType="mixed">PRESENCE OF COMMON SCALES: The Veterans Rand 12 Item Health Survey (VR-12), Lubben Social Network Scale (LSNS-6), Spanish form of Brief Resilient Coping Scale (BRCS), Perceived Stress Scale by Dr. Sheldon Cohen, CAGE questionnaire by Dr. John A. Ewing, BECK Anxiety Inventory (partial), Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS), Traumatic Exposure Severity Scale (TESS)</abstract>
            <sumDscr>
                <timePrd event="start" cycle="C1" date="2021-03-01"/>
                <timePrd event="end" cycle="C1" date="2022-07-31"/>
                <collDate event="start" cycle="C1" date="2021-03-01"/>
                <collDate event="end" cycle="C1" date="2022-07-31"/>
                <geogCover>Puerto Rico</geogCover>
                <geogCover>United States</geogCover>
                <geogUnit>Municipality</geogUnit>
                <anlyUnit>Individual</anlyUnit>
                <universe>People 78 or older of Puerto Rico living in households including those unable to answer by themselves and survivors of the original PREHCO participants from 2002-2003. </universe>
                <dataKind>survey data</dataKind>
            </sumDscr>
        </stdyInfo>
        <method>
            <dataColl>
                <sampProc>For the original sample of the first wave, a multi-stage, stratified cluster sampling was
used, using the 2000 Population and Housing Census of the United States Census
Bureau as a sampling frame. The sample included five strata and was
representative of the population aged 60 years or older in Puerto Rico and of
each of those strata.
The longitudinal follow-up of the third wave of PREHCO was carried out
on the sample of PREHCO survivors from wave 2, and maintains the
characteristics of the original sample.
In the third wave, 958 participants were
interviewed directly or through an informant proxy, of the estimated 1,299
alive at the beginning of the field work.</sampProc>
                <collMode>computer-assisted personal interview (CAPI)</collMode>
                <collMode> cognitive assessment test</collMode>
                <collMode> face-to-face interview</collMode>
                <weight>Two weights are included: one for the
targets with a direct interview (FACTORT_w3, n=617) and another for all the targets,
with a direct interview or through a proxy (FACTORTP_w3, n=811).</weight>
            </dataColl>
            <notes><p>More details can be found by visiting the <a href="https://sites.uab.edu/prehco"> project website</a>.</p></notes>
            <notes>Each dataset contains a CASEID variable which may be used for linking/merging. When using PREHCO Wave 1 or 2 data including the spouses as independent records (only targets were included in waves 3 and 4), the variable TYPE must be used in the equation (1=target, 2=spouse) since both respondent types share the CASEID.</notes>
            <anlyInfo>
                <respRate>73.7%</respRate>
            </anlyInfo>
        </method>
        <dataAccs>
            <setAvail media="online">
                <accsPlac URI="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/ICPSR/studies/39091">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</accsPlac>
            </setAvail>
            <useStmt>
                <specPerm>Additional special permissions, where applicable, are described in the restrictions field </specPerm>
                <restrctn>Access to these data is restricted. Users interested in obtaining these data must complete a Restricted Data Use Agreement,specify the reason for the request, and obtain IRB approval or notice of exemption for their research.</restrctn>
            </useStmt>
        </dataAccs>
        <notes>The public-use data files in this collection are available for access by the general public. Access does not require affiliation with an ICPSR member institution.</notes>
    </stdyDscr>
</codeBook>